cdu.edu.au 2019-12-10

# Privacy and Confidentiality Policy

Privacy and Confidentiality Policy
INTRODUCTION
The University is committed to protecting the privacy of all members of the University community. The
University will act responsibly to collect, manage, use and disclose personal information in accordance with
the Northern Territory Information Act 2002.
The University also commits to comply with the Commonwealth Privacy Act, as if it were a Commonwealth
organisation where required to abide by the Australian Privacy Principles under contracted funding
agreements from Commonwealth agencies and the Higher Education Support Act when handling students'
personal information.
STATEMENT OF AUTHORITY
The authority behind this policy is the Charles Darwin University Act 2003 part 3, section 15.
COMPLIANCE
This is a compliance requirement under the Information Act 2002 and Privacy Act 1988.
INTENT
This document sets out a framework for the protection of personal privacy and confidentiality consistent
with the University’s obligations to comply with the Northern Territory Information Privacy Principles
(IPPs), the Australian Privacy Principle and obligations of confidence.
RELEVANT DEFINITIONS
In the context of this document
Australian Privacy Principles (APPs) means the principles that set out standards, rights and obligations in
relation to handling, holding, accessing and correcting personal information as contained in Schedule 1 of
the Privacy Act 1988;
Eligible data breach means a breach of personal data security that is likely to result in serious harm to any
of the individuals to whom the data relates, and the University has been unable to prevent the likely risk of
serious harm with remedial action;
Consent means, according to the National Statement on Ethical Conduct in Human Research and Privacy
Law, agreement that is informed, specific, current and voluntary;
Governance documents means formally approved documents that outlines non-discretionary governing
principles and intentions, in order to guide University practice. Governance documents are a formal
statement of intent that mandate principles or standards that apply to the University’s governance or
operations or to the practice and conduct of its staff and students. They include the CDU Act, by-laws,
policies, procedures, guidelines, rules, codes and the Enterprise Agreement;
  Privacy and Confidentiality Policy – pol-032                                          Version: 3.02              Page 1 of 10
                   Governance Document once printed is considered an uncontrolled document. Only documents in the
                      University Governance Document Library online are considered to be the most current version.

Information Privacy Principles (IPPs) means the rules for the collection, handling, access and correcting of
personal information (including sensitive information) as contained in Schedule 2 of the Information Act;
Information and Communication Technologies (ICT) means communications, computers, enterprise
software, middleware, storage, and audio-visual systems which enable users to access, store, transmit, and
manipulate information;
Notifiable Data Breach Scheme means established requirements for entities to notify individuals and the
Australian Information Commissioner of eligible data breaches, as per the Privacy Act 1988.
Person means an individual and includes a deceased individual within the first five (5) years after death;
Personal information means information prescribed in section 4A of the Information Act that is government
information that discloses a person's identity or from which a person's identity is reasonably ascertainable,
except to the extent that:
      •    The person’s identity is disclosed only in the context of having acted in an official capacity for the
           University or another public sector organisation; and
      •    The government information discloses no other personal information about the person;
Public sector organisation means an organisation prescribed in section 5 of the Information Act and includes
the University;
Sensitive information means information prescribed in section 4 of the Information Act relating to racial or
ethnic origin, political opinions or membership of a political association, religious beliefs or affiliations,
philosophical beliefs, membership of a professional or trade association, membership of a trade union,
sexual preferences or practices, a criminal record, or health information;
Staff member means anyone employed by the University and includes all continuing, fixed-term, casual,
adjunct or honorary staff or those holding University offices or who are a member of a University
committee;
Student means a person prescribed as a student of the University in By-law 2 of the Charles Darwin
University (Student of the University) By-laws; and
University community means officials and individuals carrying out University business. This includes, but is
not limited to, all staff members, researchers, peer reviewers, students, volunteers, consultants, agents
and contractors.
POLICY
Collection of Personal Information
The University will only collect personal information that is necessary for one (1) or more of its functions
or activities.
The University will only collect personal information in a lawful, fair and not unreasonably intrusive way.
When personal information is collected from an individual, the University will take reasonable steps to
ensure that the individual is:
      •    Aware of the University’s identity and how to contact it;
  Privacy and Confidentiality Policy – pol-032                                          Version: 3.02              Page 2 of 10
                   Governance Document once printed is considered an uncontrolled document. Only documents in the
                      University Governance Document Library online are considered to be the most current version.

      •    Able to have access to the information;
      •    Aware of the purpose for which the information is collected;
      •    Aware of the persons or bodies, or classes of persons or bodies, to which the University usually
           discloses personal information;
      •    Aware of any law that requires the collection of the information; and
      •    Aware of any consequences for the individual if they do not provide all or part of the information.
If it is reasonable and practical to do so, the University will only collect personal information about an
individual from that individual. If the University collects personal information about an individual from
another person, it will take reasonable steps to ensure the individual is or has been made aware of the
matters listed above unless making the individual aware of these matters would pose a serious threat to
the life or health of a person.
The University may use and disclose personal information only in the following instances, after a written
note of the use or disclosure is made:
      •    The use or disclosure is related or directly related to the purpose for collecting it and the individual
           would reasonably expect the University to use or disclose it for that purpose;
      •    With the individual’s consent;
      •    The use or disclosure is necessary for research or the compilation or analysis of statistics in the
           public interest, and:
                o Only where the research will not be published in identifiable form; and
                o The individual’s consent cannot be reasonably obtained; and
                o The recipient of the information will not disclose the personal information; and
                o Where any health information is only used or disclosed in accordance with guidelines
                     issued by the Information Commissioner under section 86(1)(a)(iv) of the Information Act.
      •    To lessen or prevent a serious and imminent threat to a person’s life, health or safety, or of harm
           to or exploitation of a child, or serious threat to public health or safety;
      •    When required in the investigation or reporting of unlawful activity, or assisting a law
           enforcement agency;
      •    Where the use or disclosure is required or authorised by law; or
      •    In connection with the performance of the functions of the Australian Security Intelligence Office
           (ASIO) or Australian Secret Intelligence Service (ASIS) where authorised in writing.
Trans-border data flows
The University will not transfer personal information about an individual to a person (other than the
individual) outside the Northern Territory unless:
      •    The transfer is required or authorised under a law of the Northern Territory or the
           Commonwealth; or
      •    The University reasonably believes that the person receiving the information is subject to a law,
           or a contract or other legally binding arrangement, that requires the person to comply with
           principles for handling the information that are substantially similar to the Information Privacy
           Principles and Australian Privacy Principles; or
      •    The individual consents to the transfer; or
      •    The transfer is necessary for the performance of a contract between the organisation and the
           individual or for the implementation of pre-contractual measures taken in response to the
           individual's request; or
      •    The transfer is necessary for the performance or completion of a contract between the
           organisation and a third party, the performance or completion of which benefits the individual;
           or
  Privacy and Confidentiality Policy – pol-032                                          Version: 3.02              Page 3 of 10
                   Governance Document once printed is considered an uncontrolled document. Only documents in the
                      University Governance Document Library online are considered to be the most current version.

      •    All of the following apply:
                o The transfer is for the benefit of the individual;
                o It is impracticable to obtain the consent of the individual to the transfer;
                o It is likely that the individual would consent to the transfer; or
      •    The organisation has taken reasonable steps to ensure that the information will not be held, used
           or disclosed by the person to whom it is transferred, in a manner that is inconsistent with the
           Information Privacy Principles or Australian Privacy Principles.
The University will ensure that any contracts with third parties where personal information may be
transferred, contain privacy clauses requiring compliance with the Information Act and the Information
Privacy Principles and/or the Privacy Act and the Australian Privacy Principles.
Data Quality
The University will take all reasonable steps to ensure that the personal information it collects, uses or
discloses is accurate, complete and up to date.
Data Breaches
The Notifiable Data Breach Scheme, as detailed in the Privacy Act requires regulated entities to notify
affected individuals and the Australian Information Commissioner about the occurrence of eligible data
breaches.
As soon as possible after the breach has occurred, all suspected eligible data breaches must be referred to
the University’s Privacy Officer for actioning and reporting as they deem appropriate.
Information Security
The University will protect all personal information it holds from misuse, loss, unauthorised access,
modification or disclosure by:
      •    Implementing industry standards for the security and protection of personal information; and
      •    Storing information in either electronic and/or hard copy forms with access restricted to authorised
           personnel only.
Security, integrity and accuracy of information is governed by the University’s Information and
Communication Technologies Security Policy and Records Management Policy and related procedures.
The University will take reasonable steps to destroy or permanently de-identify personal information if it is
no longer needed for any purpose in accordance with the Records Management - Retention and Disposal
of University Records Procedure and Disposal Schedules.
Privacy and Confidentiality Obligations
Staff members, students, researchers, contractors and any other third party who collect use or disclose
personal information on behalf of the University have a responsibility to act consistent with the Information
Privacy Principles and Australian Privacy Principles and to take appropriate measures to avoid a breach of
confidence.
Under the Higher Education Support Act, it is an offence (punishable by fine or imprisonment), if a staff
member of the University discloses, copies or records personal information otherwise than in the course
of official employment, or causes unauthorised access to or modification of personal information held by
the University.
  Privacy and Confidentiality Policy – pol-032                                          Version: 3.02              Page 4 of 10
                   Governance Document once printed is considered an uncontrolled document. Only documents in the
                      University Governance Document Library online are considered to be the most current version.

At any time during and after employment with the University, staff members must not use, divulge, copy
or communicate any confidential information to any person without the University’s consent, regardless of
whether the other person is an employee of the University or not, except as required in the ordinary
performance of the staff member’s duties.
Unauthorised access to personal information must be reported to the University’s Privacy Officer and,
where relevant, to the responsible owner of the information system concerned. Failure to comply with this
Policy may necessitate disciplinary action.
University matters relating to individuals or non-public information must not be discussed, except where
directly related to the staff member’s role, as this may constitute a breach of confidence and therefore
misconduct.
Information and Communication Technologies Facilities
Users of the University’s Information and Communication Technologies (ICT) facilities are reminded that
anything that is written or recorded is potentially subject to subpoena or Freedom of Information requests
or other authorised access. Inappropriate use of the University’s Information and Communication
Technologies (ICT) facilities may be subject to disciplinary action.
Access and Correction
On the request of an individual, the University will take reasonable steps to inform the individual of the
kind of personal information it holds, why it holds the information and how it collects, holds, uses and
discloses the information.
On the request of an individual, the University will provide access to their personal information, except to
the extent that:
      •    Providing access would pose a serious threat to the life or health of the individual or another
           individual; or
      •    Providing access would prejudice measures for the protection of the health or safety of the public;
           or
      •    Providing access would unreasonably interfere with the privacy of another individual; or
      •    The request for access is frivolous or vexatious; or
      •    The information relates to existing or anticipated legal proceedings between the University and the
           individual and the information would not be accessible by the process of discovery or subpoena in
           those proceedings; or
      •    Providing access would reveal the intentions of the University in relation to negotiations with the
           individual in such a way that would prejudice the negotiations; or
      •    Providing access would be unlawful; or
      •    Denying access is required or authorised by law; or
      •    Providing access would be likely to prejudice an investigation of possible unlawful activity; or
      •    Providing access would be likely to prejudice one or more of the following by or on behalf of a law
           enforcement agency:
                o Preventing, detecting, investigating, prosecuting or punishing an offence or a breach of a
                     prescribed law;
                o Enforcing a law relating to the confiscation of proceeds of crime;
                o Protecting public revenue;
                o Preventing, detecting, investigating or remedying seriously improper conduct or
                     prescribed conduct;
  Privacy and Confidentiality Policy – pol-032                                          Version: 3.02              Page 5 of 10
                   Governance Document once printed is considered an uncontrolled document. Only documents in the
                      University Governance Document Library online are considered to be the most current version.

                o    Preparing for or conducting proceedings in a court or tribunal or implementing the orders
                     of a court or tribunal; or
      •    Providing access would prejudice:
                o The security or defence of the Commonwealth or a State or Territory of the
                     Commonwealth; or
                o The maintenance of law and order in the Territory.
However, where providing access would reveal evaluative information generated within the University in
connection with a commercially sensitive decision-making process, the University may give the individual
an explanation for the commercially sensitive decision rather than access to the decision.
If the University holds personal information about an individual and the individual establishes that the
information is not accurate, complete or up to date, the University will take reasonable steps to correct the
information so that it is accurate, complete and up to date.
If an individual and the University disagree about whether personal information about the individual held
by the University is accurate, complete or up to date; and
        •    The individual requests the University to associate with the information a statement to the effect
             that, in the individual's opinion, the information is inaccurate, incomplete or out of date;
        •    The University will take reasonable steps to comply with that request.
The University will provide reasons for refusing to provide access to or correct personal information.
If an individual requests the University for access to, or to correct personal information held by the
University, the University will, within a reasonable time:
        •    Provide access or reasons for refusing access; or
        •    Make the correction or provide reasons for refusing to make it; or
        •    Provide reasons for the delay in responding to the request;
If the University charges a fee for providing access to personal information, the fee will not to be excessive.
Access and amendment requests should be directed to the University’s Privacy Officer.
Notification of correction to third parties
If the University corrects personal information that the University previously disclosed to another entity,
and the individual requests the University to notify the other entity of the correction, the University will
take such steps as are reasonable in the circumstances to give that notification unless it is impracticable or
unlawful to do so.
Sensitive Information
The University will not collect sensitive information about an individual unless:
      •    The individual consents to the collection; or
      •    The University is authorised or required by law to collect the information; or
      •    The individual is:
                o Physically or legally incapable of giving consent to the collection; or
                o Physically unable to communicate his or her consent to the collection; and
                o Collecting the information is necessary to prevent or lessen a serious and imminent threat
                     to the life or health of the individual or another individual; or
  Privacy and Confidentiality Policy – pol-032                                          Version: 3.02              Page 6 of 10
                   Governance Document once printed is considered an uncontrolled document. Only documents in the
                      University Governance Document Library online are considered to be the most current version.

      •    Collecting the information is necessary to establish, exercise or defend a legal or equitable claim.
However, the University may collect sensitive information about an individual if:
      •    The collection:
                 o Is necessary for research, or the compilation or analysis of statistics, relevant to
                     government funded targeted welfare or educational services; or
                 o Is of information relating to an individual's racial or ethnic origin and is for the purpose of
                     providing government funded targeted welfare or educational services; and
      •    There is no other reasonably practicable alternative to collecting the information for that purpose;
           and
      •    It is impracticable for the organisation to seek the individual's consent to the collection.
Complaints
Questions in relation to concerns about privacy, the University’s management of personal information, or
to make a complaint, should be directed to the University’s Privacy Officer or the Northern Territory
Information Commissioner.
Non-Compliance
Members of the University community must be aware of and note that the University regards any activity,
which constitutes unacceptable access, use or disclosure as potentially serious matters that the University
may determine as misconduct or serious misconduct. Non-compliance with this policy may result in
disciplinary action and/or reference to law enforcement agencies in accordance with the relevant
legislation and University Governance Documents.
ESSENTIAL SUPPORTING INFORMATION
Internal
Charles Darwin University Act
Data Breach Response Procedure
Disposal Schedules
Email Acceptable Use Policy
Identifying Unacceptable Use of Information and Communication Technologies Procedures
Information and Communication Technologies Acceptable Use Policy
Information and Communication Technologies Security Policy
Quality Policy
Records Management Policy
External
Higher Education Support Act 2003 (Commonwealth)
  Privacy and Confidentiality Policy – pol-032                                          Version: 3.02              Page 7 of 10
                   Governance Document once printed is considered an uncontrolled document. Only documents in the
                      University Governance Document Library online are considered to be the most current version.

Information Act 2002 (NT)
Information Regulations 2010 (NT)
National Stament on Ethical Condut in Human Research 2015 (Commonwealth)
Privacy Act 1988 (Commonwealth)
Privacy Amendment (Enhancing Privacy Protection) Act 2012 (Commonwealth)
  Privacy and Confidentiality Policy – pol-032                                          Version: 3.02              Page 8 of 10
                   Governance Document once printed is considered an uncontrolled document. Only documents in the
                      University Governance Document Library online are considered to be the most current version.

                                       Document History and Version Control
Last amendment:               02 May 2018                               Next Review:          Dec 2020
Sponsor:                      Director, Strategic Services and Governance
Contact Officer:              Director, Strategic Services and Governance
Version           Date Approved            Approved by       Brief Description
1.00              04 May 2017              Council           Creation of original document and upload to CDU website.
1.01              08 Feb 2010              Governance        •    Change old policy into new format style.
                                                             •    Add statement of authority, relevant definitions,
                                                                  document history and version control and essential
                                                                  documents in keeping with new policy format.
                                                             •    Amend minor grammatical and spelling errors.
                                                             •    Amend Audit and Risk Committee to Finance, Risk and
                                                                  Review Committee to reflect change in committee
                                                                  title
                                                             •    Change Staff Services to PMD to reflect title change
1.02              29 Dec 2010              Governance        •    Convert document to new template
                                                             •    Amend PMD to Office of Human Resource Services to
                                                                  reflect title change.
                                                             •    Corporate Services changed to Director, Strategic
                                                                  Services and Governance to reflect position
                                                                  responsibility change.
                                                             •    Senior staff changed to Senior Executive. Definition
                                                                  added.
                                                             •    Definition of Senior Manager added
1.03              28 Jan 2011              Governance        •    Minor changes to spelling, grammar and formatting.
1.04              10 Jan 2012              Governance        •    Amended position titles in accordance with new
                                                                  organisational chart.
                                                             •    Update hyperlinks
                                                             •    Minor changes to grammar and formatting
                                                             •    Removal of reference to Finance, Risk and Review
                                                                  Committee as no longer active
1.05              13 Feb 2013              Governance        •    Converted document to new template
                                                             •    Updated and added hyperlinks
                                                             •    Minor changes to wording, formatting and grammar
                                                             •    Assigned document number
                                                             •    Added relevant definitions
                                                             •    Removed general responsibilities section
2.00              27 Aug 2014              Vice Chancellor   •    Major review of Policy in line with NT Information Act
                                                             •    Privacy Policy changed to Information Privacy Policy
                                                                  in line with NT Information Act
                                                             •    Definition of Senior Executive amended to reflect
                                                                  changes to position titles
Privacy and Confidentiality Policy – pol-032                                          Version: 3.02              Page 9 of 10
                 Governance Document once printed is considered an uncontrolled document. Only documents in the
                    University Governance Document Library online are considered to be the most current version.

                                                            •    Definition of Sensitive Information updated to reflect
                                                                 definition in the Act
                                                            •    Additional definitions
2.01              27 Oct 2014              Governance       •    Correction of minor grammatical errors and sentence
                                                                 structure
                                                            •    Addition of - To establish an individual’s identity for
                                                                 the purposes of access to ICT systems under
                                                                 Collection of Personal or Other Information
2.02              05 Jul 2017              Governance       •    Conversion to new Governance template due to new
                                                                 University branding
                                                            •    Updated definitions for senior executive, senior
                                                                 manage and staff member
                                                            •    Updated hyperlinks
                                                            •    Change title of reference from Northern Territory
                                                                 Government and Archives Management standards to
                                                                 Northern Territory Government Records Management
                                                                 Standards
3.00              13 Dec 2017              Governance       •    Review and amend document for compliance with the
                                                                 Commonwealth Privacy Act and HESA ;
                                                            •    Amend name from Information Privacy Policy to
                                                                 Privacy and Confidentiality Policy
                                                            •    Add definitions for APPs, ICT, person, public sector
                                                                 organisation, student, university community
                                                            •    Amendment to definitions of IPPs, personal
                                                                 information, sensitive information and staff members,
                                                            •    Remove definitions for cookies, privacy, researcher,
                                                                 senior executive, senior manager and third party
                                                            •    Remove overseas disclosure paragraph and replace
                                                                 with trans-border data flows paragraph
                                                            •    Conversion to new template due to new University
                                                                 branding
                                                            •    Updated Hyperlinks
3.01              24 Jan 2018              Governance       •    Removed duplicated paragraph
3.02              02 May 2018              Vice-Chancellor  •    Addedd definitions for Eligible data breach and
                                                                 Notifiable Data Breach Scheme
                                                            •    Amended text to include a paragraph re the reporting
                                                                 of data breaches
                                                            •    Minor rewording Collection of Personal Information
Privacy and Confidentiality Policy – pol-032                                          Version: 3.02              Page 10 of 10
                 Governance Document once printed is considered an uncontrolled document. Only documents in the
                    University Governance Document Library online are considered to be the most current version.
